All right, it's time we talked about
high noon for the new conservative
movement during the 1980s during the
presidency of Ronald Reagan. And now let
us pause so my more conservative
students can feel their feels.
[laughter]
I know you do, boo, but it's time to
shut all that down cuz I got to stuff
them mind grapes full of learning. So,
if you're ready to get them brain cows
milked, let's get to it. Okay, now
before we get to Ronald Reagan, let me
do a quick run through what we covered
in the last unit about how this modern
conservative party got started. So, it
started with the presidential candidacy
of Barry Goldwater in 1964. And although
he lost the election to that filthy
liberal Lyndon B. Johnson, Goldwater was
able to articulate on the national stage
the big emphases that would define
conservatism for the rest of the 20th
century and beyond. In other words, the
new right emphasized the transfer of
political power away from the federal
government and back to the states. And
as such, the movement represented a
clear criticism of New Deal liberalism
that had emphasized the role of the
federal government in curing any and all
economic and social ills that Americans
experienced. Now, despite the fact that
Goldwater laid an absolute egg in his
bid for the presidency, the new right
secured a significant victory in 1968
with the election of President Richard
Nixon who worked to enact many policies
that were dear to disgruntled
conservative Americans. But, since he
turned out to be a crook and thus
resigned the presidency in 1974, the
full power of this new conservatism
faltered for a moment. And so, in the
election of 1976, Americans elected the
Democrat Jimmy Carter into office. And
on his watch, America experienced a
profound economic crisis and many
perceived foreign policy failures. And
because that clearly didn't work, the
new right went ahead and got its voter
mobilization pants on for the election
of 1980. And as a result, Americans
elected the brightest star of their
right-wing universe, namely Ronald
Reagan. But, before we talk about his
conservative excellency, let me just
mention real quick that if you need help
getting an A in your class and a five on
your exam in May, you might want to
check out my Heimler review guide. It
has exclusive whole unit review videos
that are not here on YouTube and
basically everything you need to study
for that beast of an exam as fast as
possible. And if that's something you're
into, that link is in the description.
Okay, now during his campaign, Reagan
uttered a phrase that nicely summed up
his conservative priority. He said, "In
this present crisis, government is not
the solution to our problem, government
is the problem." And once Reagan was
elected, he got right to work putting
those conservative policies into action.
And those fell under two big categories.
First of all, Reagan worked to cut
taxes. To that end, he persuaded
Congress to pass the Economic Recovery
Tax Act in 1981 which significantly cut
income taxes for many Americans from the
wealthiest down to those who made the
least income. And the reason tax cuts
were a centerpiece of Reagan's policy is
because he embraced the darling economic
theory of the new right, namely
supply-side economics. Now, in order to
understand this, it might help to
compare this system to its opposite,
namely Keynesian economics, which was
behind the New Deal and Great Society
programs. So, by Keynesian reckoning,
the best way to reverse an economic
slump is for the federal government to
increase its spending even if it has to
go into debt to finance the cost. And
then, in theory, the massive amounts of
money that just got pumped into the
economy will decrease unemployment and
increase consumer spending. But, the
consequence of implementing this theory
is that the power and influence of the
federal government grows in direct
proportion to how much it spends. Now,
supply-side economics has the same end
goal, namely to revive a slumping
economy, but its means are entirely
different and deeply rooted in
conservative ideology. So, supply-siders
would argue that the best way to
stimulate the economy is by removing the
influence of the government in
Americans' lives, most notably through
tax cuts. And in theory, as the
wealthiest Americans and entrepreneurs
are able to keep more money, they will
invest that money into their businesses
which in turn will create more jobs. And
if people have jobs, they'll spend more
money and all the economic problems will
be solved. And this theory was based on
an idea from the 1920s which said that
if the richest Americans had more
wealth, then eventually that wealth
would trickle down to the rest of
society. And you know, that definitely
worked in the 1920s and did not at all
lead to the most profound economic
depression in modern history, so you
know, I'm sure it'll [snorts] work in
the 1980s. Anyway, if you want
everything I just said summed up into as
few words as possible, and I know that
you do, then here it is. Keynesian
economics focuses on the demand problem
while supply-side economics focuses on
the supply problem. Anyway, this push
for tax cuts became so central to
Reagan's presidency that it was dubbed
Reaganomics. And it turned out to have a
mixed effect. So, even with all these
drastic tax cuts rolling out,
unemployment steadily rose for the first
three years of Reagan's administration.
Additionally, now that the government
was taking in significantly less tax
revenue, the federal deficit more than
tripled. And by the way, the word
deficit is going to come up a lot in the
next few videos, and it's just referring
to the amount of money that has to be
borrowed to pay the country's bills. So,
if our bills cost this much, but tax
revenue only gives us this much, then
the deficit is the difference. So, the
federal deficit under Reagan got real
bad. And maybe you're confused because
wasn't Reagan all, "Oh, I'm about to
shrink that filthy government." Well,
yeah, he did say that, but it's a little
more complicated. So, here's why I tell
you that although Reagan pooh-poohed
federal spending, it was only a certain
kind of federal spending. Like Reagan
wanted to cut very expensive social
safety net programs enacted by liberal
administrations like Medicare and
Medicaid and Social Security. But, even
though these programs were the veritable
poster children for liberalism, many
Americans liked those programs and
refused to let them go, which meant that
the Reagan administration was still on
the hook to make those payments. Even
so, he was able to make some modest cuts
to liberal programs like Medicaid and
food stamps. But, on the other hand,
Reagan actually got all kinds of giddy
when it came to a different kind of
federal spending, namely military
spending. And as we'll talk about in
another video, Reagan spent metric
buttloads of money on military buildup,
and that cranked that federal deficit to
levels that would have made FDR proud.
Anyway, in the end, Reaganomics very
much did benefit the wealthiest
Americans. And with more money in their
pockets, the rich invested much of that
money into the stock market which saw a
significant spike in value. However, it
turned out that as wealthy Americans
gained more wealth, the benefits did not
in fact trickle down to the rest of
society, and that led to a widening gap
between the rich and the poor. And so,
over the course of his two terms, Reagan
was forced to sign bills that increased
the tax rate in order to make up some of
that lost revenue. All right, then the
second big policy push for Reagan was
the deregulation of businesses. So,
recall that over the course of the 20th
century, several new federal agencies
were created in order to oversee and
regulate various areas of America's
businesses. For example, the Department
of Labor protected workers' wages and
safety while the Environmental
Protection Agency enforced various laws
concerning pollution. And so, these and
many other agencies actually provided
good and needed services to the American
public, but there was a significant
downside. You see, many of the
regulations imposed on these businesses
cost those businesses a good chunk of
money in order to make sure that their
practices were in compliance with the
law. And with less profits available,
business owners had less money to
reinvest in their companies in order to
create more jobs and fund new research
and development. And therefore, Reagan
made it his goal to dismantle much of
the government's regulation over the
private sector. And to be clear, such
deregulation began under Carter's
administration, but Reagan kicked it
into high gear. For example, Reagan
worked to deregulate America's natural
gas industry. You see, starting in the
1930s, the federal government passed
several laws that set price controls on
natural gas. And these laws were meant
to keep natural gas affordable to
Americans, but by the 1970s, these price
controls had kept gas prices
artificially low and created huge
inefficiencies in distribution.
Therefore, Reagan gradually phased out
price controls and allowed natural gas
companies to sell their product at
market rates on the belief that the free
market could better facilitate supply
and demand than government regulation.
And as a result, natural gas production
increased, which in turn lowered prices,
and all that created a more stable
supply. Additionally, in order to roll
back the influence of other regulatory
agencies, Reagan appointed leaders to
those departments who were ideologically
opposed to the missions of those
agencies. For example, Reagan appointed
a woman with serious
anti-environmentalist beliefs to lead
the EPA. And the result was that the
agency significantly eased up on
enforcing environmental protection laws,
so you know, that's fun. Okay, now we
spent quite a bit of time talking about
Ronald Reagan, but that's because his
policy agenda really did set the stage
for national politics throughout the
rest of the 20th century. And those
commitments resulted in ongoing
political and cultural debates that have
lasted up to the present day, and that's
what we're going to focus on here in
this last section. But first, let me do
a quick speed run through the next few
presidents so that these debates are
going to make more sense. After Reagan
came the Republican George H.W. Bush who
promised a kinder, gentler conservatism.
And while Bush promised not to raise
taxes, I guess that he forgot that
Reagan handed him a massive, honking
budget deficit, and so Bush was forced
to raise taxes, and it turned out that
Americans didn't like that. And so,
after Bush served a single term,
Americans voted in the Democrat Bill
Clinton who in many ways looked a lot
like a conservative on economic issues,
but more like a liberal on social
issues. Okay, so now let's get to the
ongoing liberal-conservative debates in
the last decades of the 20th century.
Okay, first of all, liberals and
conservatives debated the value of free
trade agreements. So, in 1994, President
Bill Clinton signed the North American
Free Trade Agreement or NAFTA, which
lowered barriers to trade between
Canada, the United States, and Mexico.
And essentially, the agreement turned
these three countries into a powerful
economic unit that could compete on the
global market with the newly formed
European Union. Now, conservatives who
wholeheartedly believed in the forces of
the unregulated free market cheered this
agreement. it aligned with Reagan-era
commitments toward deregulation since
removing tariffs fosters competition
which ultimately increases efficiency
and lowers prices. But, liberals on the
other hand argued that as barriers to
trade were stripped away, manufacturing
jobs would rapidly relocate to Mexico.
And if that happened at scale, then
millions of American workers would be
out of jobs while the corporate elite
got richer since they no longer had to
pay fair wages. And as it turned out,
both sides were kind of right. See, the
agreement did cause a significant uptick
in unregulated trade which resulted in
the loss of significant amounts of
American manufacturing jobs
relocated their operations where labor
was cheaper. And to be fair, that whole
debate is not as tidy as I just
explained. Like some conservatives
opposed NAFTA while some liberals
endorsed it, but on the whole, that's
how it was. Okay, the second debate was
about the proper scope of government
safety net policies. So, Bill Clinton
made it a priority of his administration
to enact sweeping healthcare reform
because medical costs were skyrocketing
and millions of Americans could not
afford health insurance. Therefore, he
proposed a complicated policy that would
have allowed the federal government to
play a significant role in offering
healthcare at minimal cost to Americans.
And not surprisingly, congressional
conservatives loudly protested what to
them sounded like the old New Deal kind
of government overreach into the lives
of Americans. And ultimately, the bill
proposed by Clinton was voted down by
Congress. Anyway, here's where I tell
you that the rancorous debate over that
healthcare bill significantly influenced
the midterm elections later that year in
1994. And as it turned out, Republicans
won majorities in both houses of
Congress and soon began to wield that
power to bring conservatism back to the
American public. And the most visible
effort on this front came from Georgia
representative Newt Gingrich who became
the first conservative speaker of the
house in nearly 50 years. And during his
campaign, Gingrich courted conservative
voters by presenting what he called a
Contract with America. It outlined a
whole host of conservative policies that
on the whole would dismantle the corrupt
liberal welfare state while working for
further deregulation of industries and
generally shrinking the size of the
federal government. But ultimately
Gingrich was such a bombastic man with
little patience for compromise and that
meant that relatively few of his
contract policies were enacted. Okay,
and then the third continuing debate
centered on the push for traditional
versus progressive social values. So
picking up on the arguments from the
last period conservatives continued to
argue that liberal policies had led to a
manifest decay in traditional family
values. For example, conservatives
complained that the 1973 Roe v. Wade
decision legalizing abortion was an
attack against the rights of the unborn.
However, equally upsetting to
conservatives was the growing influence
of second wave feminism and the women's
liberation movement. You see, the push
for women's social equality challenged
the conservative notion that society
function best when men and women submit
to their assigned gender roles, which
essentially meant that men do the work
and women stay at home and serve. And
then adding fuel to this particular fire
was the intertwining of evangelical
Christian beliefs with conservative
Republican politics. You see, the
evangelicals came equipped with a
fistful of Bible verses that they
believed commanded female submission.
And with evangelical leaders like Pat
Robertson emphasizing such teachings
through his enormously popular show The
700 Club, conservatism was infused with
a powerful religious zeal. And so it was
difficult to discern whether the New
Right's opposition to abortion concerned
the rights of the unborn or whether it
was more of a reaction to women upending
their preferred norm for family
structure. And then another example of
the conservative traditional values
debate was the AIDS crisis in the 1980s.
Now because of this novel virus first
began spreading rapidly among gay men,
the conservative Reagan administration
did very little to address the tens of
thousands of Americans who were dying
from the disease. some Christian leaders
of the New Right including Pat Robertson
claimed that the reason the disease was
killing gay men is because they were
under God's judgment for their embrace
of a perverted lifestyle. Anyway, the
point is Reagan had won the presidency
in no small part thanks to the support
of the Christian right and so he worried
that any move on his part to address the
epidemic might alienate them. Even so,
eventually the Reagan administration did
act to address this crisis but it was
far too little, far too late. But on the
flip side, this injustice mobilized gay
activists to organize the ACT UP
movement through which they staged
public protest aimed at securing better
funding for AIDS research and relief.
And finally, the fourth major debate was
about immigration policy. So immigration
numbers rose significantly during the
1970s after legal quotas were removed in
1965 and a large portion of those
immigrants came from Mexico. And in
response to such a surge, conservatives
themselves were divided as to the proper
response. Some conservatives took up the
old argument that immigrants stole jobs
from Americans and they were unable to
fully assimilate into American society.
But others, although a minority,
attempted to remind everyone that
America was largely built on the
benefits conferred by immigrants, not
least their contribution to the economy.
And as it happened, Reagan fashioned a
compromise between these antagonistic
groups with the passage of the
Immigration Reform and Control Act of
1986. This law allowed undocumented
immigrants who had lived in the United
States for a certain period of time to
remain in the country and work toward
gaining their citizenship. But on the
other hand, it also enacted economic
penalties for businesses who hired
undocumented immigrants. Okay, you can
click here to watch my other Unit 9
videos or you can click here to grab my
A Push Heimler review guide which has
everything you need to help you get a
five on your exam in May. I'm glad you
came around and I'll catch you on the
flip flop. Heimler out.